Tiago Guerreiro

PhD, Assistant Professor, Researcher

LASIGE, Faculdade de Ciências da Universidade de Lisboa https://tjvguerreiro.github.io // tjvg@di.fc.ul.pt



Short Bio

Tiago Guerreiro is an Assistant Professor at the University of Lisbon (Faculty of Sciences) and a researcher at LaSIGE. His main areas of expertise are HCl, Accessibility, and Mobile Computing. His research is focused on improving health, accessibility, and privacy, through and to technology, following a user-centred design approach. He has worked closely with people with motor, cognitive, and visual impairments, both in understanding their abilities, and in empowering them with alternative and adaptive interfaces. In these areas, he has published 75+ peer-reviewed papers. He received awards for 8 papers, including at CHI, ASSETS, SOUPS and MHCl, the flagship venues for HCl, Accessible Computing, Usable Privacy and Mobile HCl, and a Best of Computing award in 2016. He was a PC member for 40+ conferences. He was the Web for All General and Program Chair, in 2016 and 2015, respectively, and has been an associate chair for CHI in the last five editions, among many other service roles. He participated in 10+ EU projects. He was an expert evaluator for H2020 EU calls and is currently an invited expert supporting the EC in implementing the Web Accessibility Directive. He teaches Mobile Computing, Web Applications, Game Design, and Data Science courses and currently advises 12 MSc and 2 PhD students. He is a founding and current member of his institution Ethics Review Board.

Education

PhD, Information Systems and Computer Engineering

Instituto Superior Técnico, Universidade de Lisboa

September 2012, "User-Sensitive Mobile Interfaces: Accounting for Individual Differences amongst the Blind"

MSc, Information Systems and Computer Engineering

Instituto Superior Técnico, Universidade de Lisboa

July 2008, "Myographic Mobile Accessibility for Tetraplegics"

BSc, Computer Science and Engineering

Instituto Superior Técnico, Universidade de Lisboa

September 2005

Academic Positions

Assistant Professor

Departamento de Informática, Faculdade de Ciências da Universidade de Lisboa **September 2011 - present**

Invited Assistant Professor

Faculdade de Engenharia, Universidade Católica Portuguesa September 2010 - February 2012

Teaching Assistant

Departamento de Informática, Instituto Superior Técnico, Universidade de Lisboa September 2006 - February 2008

Selected Honors

ACM Best of Computing, 2016

For his 2016 SOUPS paper "Snooping on Mobile Phones: Prevalence and Trends"

Honourable Mention, 2016

ACM International Conference on Human-Computer Interaction with Mobile Devices and Services

Distinguished Paper Award, 2016

Usenix Symposium on Usable Privacy and Security

Best Paper Award, 2015

ACM Conference on Interactive Tabletops and Surfaces

Best Paper Award, 2014

ACM Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems

Best Student Paper Award, 2011

ACM Conference on Computers and Accessibility

Best Short Paper Award, 2011

IFIP Conference on Human-Computer Interaction

Selected International Peer-Reviewed Publications^{1,2}

Investigating Laboratory and Everyday Typing Performance of Blind Users

Hugo Nicolau, Kyle Montague, Tiago Guerreiro, André Rodrigues, Vicki L. Hanson **ACM Transactions on Accessible Computing (TACCESS), 2017**

Characterizing Social Insider Attacks on Facebook

Wali Usmani, Diogo Marques, Ivan Beschastnikh, Konstantin Beznosov, Tiago Guerreiro, Luís Carriço **ACM Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI), 2017**

Snooping on Mobile Phones: Prevalence and Trends

Diogo Marques, Ildar Muslukhov, Tiago Guerreiro, Luis Carriço, Konstantin Beznosov Twelfth Symposium on Usable Privacy and Security (SOUPS), 2016, Distinguished Paper Award

Blind People Interacting with Large Touch Surfaces: Strategies for One and Two-handed Exploration

Tiago Guerreiro, Kyle Montague, João Guerreiro, Rafael Nunes, Hugo Nicolau, Daniel Gonçalves **ACM Conference on Interactive Tabletops and Surfaces (ITS), 2015, Best Paper Award**

Getting Smartphones to TalkBack: Understanding the Smartphone Adoption Process of Blind Users

André Rodrigues, Kyle Montague, Hugo Nicolau, Tiago Guerreiro

ACM SIGACCESS Conference on Computers and Accessibility (ASSETS), 2015

Typing Performance of Blind Users: Analysis of Touch Behaviors, Learning Effect, and In-Situ Usage

¹ Complete list can be found at https://tjvguerreiro.github.io/publications/

² Premiere conferences in CS and HCI (e.g., ASSETS, CHI, MHCI, ITS) are highly selective and intended for archival papers only. These often exceed journals in their selectivity, visibility, and impact. Submissions undergo multiple rounds of review before being accepted. Please see a <u>study comparing the impact of conference papers and journals in these areas</u> (http://portal.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=1743546.1743569).

Hugo Nicolau, Kyle Montague, André Rodrigues, Tiago Guerreiro, Vicki Hanson **ACM SIGACCESS Conference on Computers and Accessibility (ASSETS), 2015**

Usage of Subjective Scales in Accessibility Research

Shari Trewin, Diogo Marques Tiago Guerreiro

ACM SIGACCESS Conference on Computers and Accessibility (ASSETS), 2015

Friendsourcing the Unmet Needs of People with Dementia

João Martins, Oliver Schnell, José Carilho, Carlos Duarte, Francisco Couto, Luís Carriço, Tiago Guerreiro **The Web 4 All Conference (W4A), 2014**

B#: Chord-based Correction for Multitouch Braille Input

Hugo Nicolau, Kyle Montague, João Guerreiro, Tiago Guerreiro, Vicki Hanson **ACM Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI), 2014, Best Paper Award**

Mobile Touch Screen Uls: Bridging the Gap between Motor Impaired and Able-Bodied Users

Hugo Nicolau, Tiago Guerreiro, Daniel Gonçalves, Joaquim Jorge Universal Access in the Information Society (UAIS), 2014

UbiBraille: Designing and Evaluating a Vibrotactile Braille-Reading Device

Hugo Nicolau, João Guerreiro, Tiago Guerreiro, Luís Carriço

ACM SIGACCESS Conference on Computers and Accessibility (ASSETS), 2013

Blind People and Mobile Touch-based Text-Entry: Acknowledging the Need for Different Flavors

João Oliveira, Tiago Guerreiro, Hugo Nicolau, Joaquim Jorge, Daniel Gonçalves

ACM SIGACCESS Conference on Computers and Accessibility (ASSETS), 2011, Best Student Paper Award

Selected Press

Mexer no telemóvel de outra pessoa? Um em cada cinco já o fez, P3 - Público, Julho de 2016

1 in 5 snoop on a phone belonging to a friend or loved one, Boing boing, Julho de 2016

A tecnologia que guia os cegos, Público, Maio de 2016

Aplicação para android como ferramenta para terapia com autistas, O Observador, Julho de 2014

Portugueses criam aplicação que ajuda autistas, TVI 24, Junho de 2014

SmartPhone para cegos: Uma invenção portuguesa, Visão, Junho de 2014

Cientistas portugueses melhoram o uso de smartphones para cegos, Público, Junho de 2014

Braille Technology moves into the 21st century, The Raw Story, Junho de 2014

Good vibrations bring Braille into the 21st century, The Conversation, Maio de 2014

Site mostra citações de Fernando Pessoa nas redes sociais, Público, Junho de 2013

Design Inclusivo, Sociedade Civil, Junho de 2012.

SMS para Cegos, Pública, 21 de Novembro de 2010

BloNo. Telemóvel para cegos à espera de empresas interessadas, i, 1 de Julho de 1010

Telemóveis para cegos, Ovo de Colombo, SIC, Maio de 2010

BloNo: Acessibilidade Móvel para Cegos, Programa 2010, RTP2, Agosto de 2009

Telemóveis para Cegos, inovar.te, n°4, pp. 20-21, Abril/Maio de 2007

Invited Talks and Keynotes

Tecnologia ao Serviço da Pessoa com Demência e Seus Cuidadores

I Seminário Envelhece AtivaMENTE, Liga dos Amigos da Terceira Idade, Setúbal, Maio de 2016

From Tabletops to Smartwatches: Layers Beyond Physical Access

Handicap 2016, La recherche au service de la qualité de vie et de l'autonomie, Paris, Junho de 2016

A Tecnologia ao Serviço da Pessoa com Demência

Cuidados a Prestar na Demência, 2º Encontro de Profissionais, Projecto Cuidar Melhor – Auditório da Casa das Histórias – Paula Rego, Novembro de 2015.

Touchscreen Accessibility: From Tablets to Smartwatches

ENVITER'15- European Network For Vision Impairment Training Education & Research Annual Conference, ULusófona, Lisboa, Portugal

A Tecnologia ao Serviço da Pessoa com Demência

Café Memória – Fórum Apoio, Algés, Junho de 2015

Café Memória – Colombo, Lisboa, Junho de 2015

Café Memória – Espaço Santa Casa, Santa Clara, Lisboa, Maio de 2015

Café Memória – Chiado, Lisboa, Maio de 2015

Assistive Technologies for Spinal Cord Injured People

Instituto Superior Técnico, Universidade de Lisboa. Lisboa, Portugal. Maio de 2015.

Accessibility Layers: Beyond Access

Universidade Federal do Ceará, Fortaleza, Brasil. Dezembro de 2014.

Designing for Extremes and All in Between

University of Dundee, Dundee, Scotland. Março de 2014.

Selected Professional Service

Chairing

CHI'14-18 Associate Chair, ASSETS'16 Experience Reports Chair, W4A'16 General Chair, ASSETS'15 Local Chair, W4A'15 Program Chair, ACM CHI Workshop on Inconspicuous Interaction 2014 Chair, ... (20+)

Program Committee

ACM CHI (2014-2018), ACM IUI (2012-2017), ACM ASSETS (2010-2017), (50+)

Journal Reviewing

Transactions on Accessible Computing (20111, 2012, 2013, 2014, 2015, 2016), Transactions on Computer-Human Interaction (2013, 2014, 2015, 2016), International Journal of Serious Games (2015), Transactions on Haptics (2015), Robotics and Autonomous Systems (2015), International Journal on Human-Computers Studies (2012, 2013, 2016, 2017), Universal Access in the Information Society (2012, 2014), Interacting with Computers (2012), Intelligent Systems in Accounting, Finance and Management (2012)

Advising

2 PhD Students (ongoing), 12 MSc Students (ongoing), 30 MSc Students (finished)